Finding aid to the Lesbian Bisexual Transgender Alliance records CA.MS.00112
Smith College Archives
Lesbian Bisexual Transgender Alliance records
1971-2004
Smith College Archives
Lesbian Bisexual Transgender Alliance
CA.MS.00112
0.833 linear feet (2 containers)
Student organization. The records of the Lesbian Bisexual Transgender Alliance document the organization's history, maintenance, goals, and obstacles met while trying to attain those goals. The records also provide an insight into the social issues surrounding lesbianism and how they've changed since the organization's inception, while at the same time providing a look at the lifecycle and campus perception of the LBTA. Types of materials include correspondence, surveys, campus flyers, photographs, and newspaper articles.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records of the Lesbian Bisexual Transgender Alliance were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Arrangement
This records are arranged in six series:
I. Administrative Records
II. Correspondence
III. Events
IV. Photographs
V. Surveys
VI. Newsclippings
Biographical / Historical
The Lesbian Bisexual Transgender Alliance grew out of several significant events in the 1970s. In 1973, the newly formed Women's Resource Center hosted Smith College's first "Women's Weekend", at which a workshop on lesbianism was held. From this workshop, an underground organization called Sophia's Sisters, was founded. This organization was denied chartering and funding, and being unable to create a visible campus presence, was forced to disband in 1975. The Lesbian Alliance (LBA) was founded the following year (and chartered in 1977) by Jennet Inglis and Liza McKinley, both Class of 1978. Despite frequent hostility and funding difficulties, the organization grew. In 1984, the college administration closed Hover House, a predominantly lesbian resident house. However, by this time, the LBA had a strong foothold on campus, and was gaining widespread acceptance. In 1988, as bisexual women gained more visibility and the lesbian/gay rights movements expanded, the Lesbian Alliance officially changed its name to the Lesbian Bisexual Alliance. The organization changed its name to the Lesbian Bisexual Transgender Alliance (LBTA) sometime between 1999 and 2002.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Lesbian Bisexual Transgender Alliance consist mainly of administrative material that document the organization's history and maintenance. There is also a large component of correspondence to and from campus administrators, outlining the organization's goals, and examining the obstacles met while trying to attain those goals. This is a collection that may be useful to anyone researching the lifecycle and campus perception of student organizations. These records also provide an insightful look into the social issues surrounding lesbianism and how they've changed over the decades since the organization's inception. Types of materials include correspondence, meeting minutes, budget proposals, surveys, campus flyers, photographs, and newspaper articles. Material is arranged chronologically.
Lesbians--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Bisexual women--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Women college students--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Smith College--Students.
- Series I. Administrative Records, 1976-2004
  - History, charters, by-laws, structure., 1976-1995 (Box 3016)
  - Financial material, budget proposals, 1976-2001 (Box 3016)
  - Board meeting minutes and agendas, 1976-2004 (Box 3016)
  - Board notebook [disassembled], 1992-1993 (Box 3016)
  - Bias, memos and material to and from LBTA relating to bias crimes, complaints on campus, and the forming of the Committee on Bias Complaints., 1976-1993 (Box 3016)
  - LBTA space/library, 1985-1992 (Box 3016)
  - Newsletters, 1977-1993 (Box 3016)
  - Miscellaneous notes and memoranda, 1977-1993 (Box 3016)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1976-1993
  - Letters and reminisces of LBA members, others, Includes student paper "The Lesbian Alliance: A Study of Minority Group and Liberal Tolerance", 1979 (Box 3016)
  - General, 1976-1993 (Box 3016)
- Series III. Events, 1976-2003
  - Flyers, 1976-1999 (Box 3016.1)
  - Flyers, undated (Box 3016.1)
  - Coming Out day, 1990-1993 (Box 3016.1)
  - Workshops/seminars
    - LBA seminar evaluations questions panel, 1977 (Box 3016.1)
  - Miscellaneous programs and schedule of events, 1977-2000 (Box 3016.1)
    - Five College Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Studies course offerings, 1991-1992. (Box 3016.1)
- Series IV. Photographs, 1988-1994
  - Photographs: members, events (Box 3016.1)
- Series V. Surveys, 1982-1993
  - Surveys: Mainly material related to 1983 student survey, includes correspondence to and from Jill Conway. Other survey sample forms., 1982-1991 (Box 3016.1)
  - Student survey results, May 1983 (Box 3016.1)
- Series VI. Newsclippings, 1971-1993
  - Clippings from The Sophian, n.d. or annotated., 1971-1991 (Box 3016.1)
  - Hover House press packet, 1983-1984 (Box 3016.1)
  - Clippings and articles from other Smith publications., 1976-1992 (Box 3016.1)
  - Clippings and articles from non-Smith publications., 1983-1993 (Box 3016.1)
  - Index to article titles in The Smith College Sophian, see Reading Room for originals.
    - Letters to editor:
      - 1971
        - "Homosexuality," The Sophian, February 4, 1971 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Homosexuals supported," The Sophian, February 12, 1971 (Box 3016.1)
        - Livesay, Debbie, "Homosexuals supported," The Sophian, February 12, 1971 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Gay world," The Sophian, February 12, 1971 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1975
        - Miller, Melissa, "Gay/straight split explained," The Sophian, October 16, 1975 (Box 3016.1)
        - McKnight, Michele, "Gay/straight article questioned," The Sophian, October 23, 1975 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1979
        - Jessop, Susan and Pincus, Betsy, "Do not ignore Lesbian Alliance," The Sophian, February 1, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Marresse, Mary-Lynn, "Alumna sees growing paranoia," The Sophian, April 2, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Perry, Vanessa, and Ellman, Barat, "Anti-Lesbian reaction disappoints," The Sophian, April 2, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Unsworth, Richard P., Rev., "Chaplains address Lesbian Alliance funding," The Sophian, April 2, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Herboldsheimer, Ramona, "How the Lesbian Alliance uses funds," The Sophian, March 5, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Reidenbach, Faith, "Secretary of SFC explains Lesbian Alliance budget recommendations," The Sophian, March 5, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Bushby, Faith B., "A matter of sexual preference," The Sophian, March 8, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Jopling, Mary, "Silent majority: speak out," The Sophian, March 8, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - McKnight, Lisa, "SFC: Re-analyze proposals," The Sophian, March 8, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Miller, Sandra, "Not for all women," The Sophian, March 8, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Geibel, Victoria, "Member of "silent majority" speaks out," The Sophian, March 12, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Peterson, Lisa, "Obtain unity by funding "factions"," The Sophian, March 12, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Reidenbach, Faith, "Letter's argument refuted," The Sophian, March 12, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1982
        - "Rumor hurts," The Sophian, October 7, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Harassment fosters learning," The Sophian, September 30, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Workshops help overcome homophobia," The Sophian, November 11, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
        - Correction, November 11, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Clearing confusion," The Sophian, November 15, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
        - Women's Resource Center, "Inadequate procedure," The Sophian, November 15, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1983
        - Wallace, Barrie, "Freedom of expression," The Sophian, April 21, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Lesbian Alliance: Smith is for Lovers," The Sophian, April 28, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - Stout, Kathryn, "Lesbian Alliance: Smith is for Lovers," The Sophian, April 28, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1985
        - Griffiths, Heidi and Lavine, Rachel, "Invasion of privacy," The Sophian, October 3, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - Corvi, Anne, "Lesbian Alliance clarified," The Sophian, October 3, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Reactionary behavior at LA meeting," The Sophian, October 21, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Sexual definition raises conflict," The Sophian, October 24, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1990
        - Kamps, Julie, "Student endorses Coming Out Day," The Sophian, October 11, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - Kressy, Sarah, "Pink triangles represent love," The Sophian, October 11, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - Moore, Betsy, "Students praise Tenney residents for courage," The Sophian, December 3, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Reports show need for action," The Sophian, December 3, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - "RCA condemns incidents," The Sophian, December 3, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - Kavner, Julie, "Tyler House victimized in incident," The Sophian, December 6, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1991
        - Parrot, Jodi M. and Klotko, Lebasi, "Lose the hatred," The Sophian, April 4, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Adamson, Joanna, "Context misunderstood," The Sophian, April 11, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Bolyn, Elizabeth, "Queers read this unjustly criticized," The Sophian, April 11, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Godley, Sophie, "Act as straight allies for gays," The Sophian, April 8, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Rhodes-Conway, Satya, "Act against homophobia," The Sophian, April 25, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1993
        - Feldwick, Jennifer A., "Campus chalking," The Sophian, October 21, 1993 (Box 3016.1)
        - Miller, Jennifer, "Campus chalking," The Sophian, October 21, 1993 (Box 3016.1)
    - Articles
      - 1973
        - Hill, Amy, "Weekend workshop helps lesbians examine dilemma," The Sophian, April 12, 1973 (Box 3016.1)
        - Levin, Ann, "Lesbian role examined," The Sophian, November 8, 1973 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Dialogue: Sophiasisters cope with misunderstanding," The Sophian, November 1, 1973 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1976
        - Bishop, Daphne, "Conway expresses views on controversial issues," The Sophian, Vol. 25, no. 7, November 11, 1976 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Women's Resource Center redefining purpose," The Sophian, November 15, 1976 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1979
        - Kuropat, Rosemary, "Gay students share experiences," The Sophian, February 26, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Brickell, Sally Ann, "SFC proposes '79-80 budget to Senate," The Sophian, March 1, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - McCormick, Cindy, "Activities fee to increase," The Sophian, March 8, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Smith, Robin Lynn, "Groups get additional funds," The Sophian, March 8, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Murtagh, Anne T., "No funds to factions," The Sophian, March 8, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Make a study of the budget," The Sophian, March 12, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
        - Salzer, Elizabeth A.J., "View fellow students with compassion," The Sophian, March 12, 1979 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1982
        - Chapman, Cate, "Women's Resource Center seeks new image," The Sophian, September 30, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
        - Burns, Suzanne, "Holly Near to give concert at Smith," The Sophian, October 7, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
        - Yum, Cathy, "Lesbian workshop dispels fears," The Sophian, November 8, 1982 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1983
        - The Smith College Lesbian Alliance, "Golden re-appointment decision questioned," The Sophian, January 31, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - Carlisle, Kate, "Four ages of women," The Sophian, April 28, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Lesbians organize event," The Sophian, April 28, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - Mannis, Wendy, "Lesbians seek end to harassment,", February 14, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - Hassett, Jody, "Administration puts restrictions on student run workshops," The Sophian, October 3, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - Garrow, Suzanne, "Workshop deferral checks student's freedom," The Sophian (typed draft in LBTA records), October 3, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Alliance demands changes in School policy," The Sophian, October 24, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
        - Mahoney, Eileen, "Conway accepts advice, houses rate workshops," The Sophian, vol.32, no. 16, November 14, 1983 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1984
        - "Senate continues budget hearings of College organizations," The Sophian, March 8, 1984 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1985
        - "Alliance reviews plans," The Sophian, Vol. 34, no. 5, September 30, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - O'Laughlin, Paula, "Student questions Smith liberalism," The Sophian, October 3, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - Streeter, Jane, "Recognizing the lesbian/straight split: everyone's loss," The Sophian, October 21, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - Lavine, Rachel, "Target basic issue, realize heterosexual privilege," The Sophian, November 11; 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Porn on campus," The Sophian, November 11, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - Chapman, Laura, "Feminism includes all," The Sophian, November 11, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - LeBlanc, Adrian Nichole, "Speaker expounds on gay rights," The Sophian, Vol. 34, no. 16, November 14, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
        - "National Gay Task Force examines lesbian and gay ideas," The Sophian, November 14, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1989
        - "Special Edition: Racial Tension at Smith," vol. 37, no. 41, 1989 (Box 3016.1)
        - Fronek, Laurie, "Student receives homophobic note," The Sophian, March 9, 1989 (Box 3016.1)
        - Rahmin, Jesmin, "Religious beliefs do not imply homophobia," The Sophian, March 9, 1989 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1990
        - Fitzgerald, Alexandra, "College forms subcommittee on lesbian and bisexual issues," The Sophian, Vol. 39, no. 28, February; 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - "Information leads to an informed choice," The Sophian, April 16, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - Earnshaw, Nancy, "LBA coordinates annual march," The Sophian, April 26, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - Krasik, Erin, "SGA sponsors B-Glad Week to promote awareness," The Sophian, vol.39, no. 37, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
        - Clemons, Kendra, "Report of homophobic incidents increases on campus," The Sophian, vol. 40, no. 20, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1991
        - "HIV testing needed at Smith," The Sophian, February 21, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Ulrich, Gretchen, "LBA resources available," The Sophian, April 18, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Wetherall, Diana Rael, "Anonymous HIV testing to be offered by health services," The Sophian, vol. 41, no. 6, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Imajo, Anika and Miller, Susan, "Campus events reflect recent legislation," The Sophian, December 5, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Clemons, Kendra, "Investigation follows threatening incident," The Sophian, vol. 40, no. 22, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
        - Weinberg, Emily, "Gayla Week celebrates lesbian, gay and bisexual culture," vol. 40, no. 33, March 11, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
      - 1993
        - "Discourse not anonymity,", October 21, 1993 (Box 3016.1)
        - Drew, Maria Elena, "Anonymous signs counter chalking on Coming Out Day," The Sophian, Vol. 43, no. 4, October 21, 1993 (Box 3016.1)
        - Fischer, Karin and Potash, Jennifer, "Smith conservatives celebrate Coming Out Day," The Sophian, vol. 43, no. 10, 1993 (Box 3016.1)
    - (undated articles, see LBTA records)
      - "Comments on chalking," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Farabee, Mindy, "LBA coffee house provides more than just Folger's,", undated (Box 3016.1)
      - "Groups react to formal changes," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Suszko, Stephanie, "Discrimination of the future?," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Bergin, Caitlin, "Smith women consider family values," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - "Women's needs come first," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Bryant, Linda, "Homophobia is everywhere," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Anonymous, "To the editors," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Laehmann, Kathrine, "Religion major defines Alliance," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Davis, Sue and Wender, Jocelyn, "T-shirts," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Baskys, Loretta, "More biblical passages quoted," The Sophian, undated (Box 3016.1)
      - Burger, Ann M., "Homophobia unacceptable," The Sophian, 1990 (Box 3016.1)
      - Godley, Sophie, "National Coming Out Day,", 1991 (Box 3016.1)
    - Full issues collected: (see bound volumes in reading room)
      - The Sophian, vol. 34, no. 16, 1985 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 34, no. 24, 1986 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 34, no. 29, 1986 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 39, no. 8, 1989 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 39, no. 19, 1989 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 40, no. 20, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 40, no. 22, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 40, no. 25, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 40, no. 26, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 40, no. 33, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 40, no. 41, 1991 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 43, no. 4, 1993 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, vol. 43, no. 10, 1993 (Box 3016.1)
      - The Sophian, March 9, 1989 (Box 3016.1)